Guide to the Elizabeth Baldwin Harris diaries, 1858-1893, 1958
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Elizabeth Baldwin Harris diaries 1858-1893, 1958
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Harris, Elizabeth Baldwin Wiley.
0.5 Linear Feet 20 Items
Elisabeth Baldwin Wiley Harris was a resident of a large plantation near Sparta, Hancock County, Georgia.
The bulk of the collection consists of six volumes and fragments of a manuscript diary with daily entries from 1862 to 1893, written by Elizabeth Harris. Although there is a fragment of the diary dated 1858, the daily entries begin Jan. 4, 1862, and continue, with brief interruptions for illnesses and family crises, until Oct. 26, 1893. Harris occasionally mentions local and national politics, events connected with the Civil War, and slavery, but most of the entries concern the weather, family matters, births, deaths, illnesses, the state of her soul, and daily activities. The collection also contains one letter dated 1860, two letters dated 1957 and 1958, and a genealogy from the donor which gives background information about the author and her family.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Elizabeth Baldwin Harris diaries were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a deposit in 1956.
Biographical Note
Elizabeth Baldwin Wiley Harris was born in Hancock County, Georgia, August 24, 1821, the daughter of Eliza DeWitt and William Wiley, a well-to-do planter. She was one of four children. The family later migrated to New York. In 1845 Elizabeth married James Martin Harris, also of Hancock County, who owned a plantation there of 10,000 acres. Eliza was a descendent of the DeWitt family, which came from Rochelle, France, and founded New Rochelle, N.Y. Avis and Cornelia were sisters of Eliza. Elizabeth B. (Wiley) and James M. Harris had no children, but they adopted Moses Wiley, a son of her brother Samuel Wiley and Sarah (Carnes) Wiley. Moses Wiley Harris was the father of the donor, Mrs. Elizabeth B.H. Holmes. Fate, the overseer of the Harris plantation, was the son of an African prince. [Information given by Mrs. Elizabeth Baldwin Harris Holmes and from information in the collection.]
Collection Overview
The bulk of the collection consists of six volumes and fragments of a manuscript diary with daily entries from 1862 to 1893, written by Elizabeth Harris. Although there is a fragment of the diary dated 1858, the daily entries begin Jan. 4, 1862, and continue, with brief interruptions for illnesses and family crises, until Oct. 26, 1893. Harris occasionally mentions local and national politics, events connected with the Civil War, and slavery, but most of the entries concern the weather, family matters, births, deaths, illnesses, the state of her soul, and daily activities. The collection also contains one letter dated 1860, two letters dated 1957 and 1958, and a genealogy from the donor which gives background information about the author and her family.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Harris, Elizabeth Baldwin Wiley
Harris family
Plantation life -- Georgia
Plantation owners' spouses -- Georgia
Women -- Diaries
Georgia -- Social conditions
Hancock County (Ga.) -- Genealogy
Hancock County (Ga.) -- History
Sparta (Ga.) -- History
Diaries
Contents of Collection
- Elizabeth Baldwin Harris diaries, 1858-1893, 1958, 1 box
  - Diary (fragment), 1858 (Box 1)
  - Diary, 1862 Jan. 4-1863 Nov. 25 (Box 1)
  - Diary, 1863 Nov. 26-1867 Jan. 12 (Box 1)
  - Diary, 1867 Jan. 12-1873 Dec. 27 (Box 1)
  - Diary, 1873 Dec. 28-1879 Dec. 31 (Box 1)
  - Diary, 1880 Jan. 1-1886 Apr.30 (Box 1)
  - Diary, 1886 May 1-1893 Oct. 10 (Box 1)
  - Genealogy (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1860, 1957, 1958 (Box 1)